[SPEAKER_01]: Any specific questions?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, there's a few things I want to talk to you about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's one about assuming the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: If one assumes the senses, then, on account of that, feelings grow, and the mind becomes
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind becomes damaged with covetousness, cruelty, and acts... and, yeah, this is just a heaping up of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: That one is said to be far from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when seeing a sight, mindfulness becomes confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: If attention is focused on the pleasant aspect,
[SPEAKER_00]: Doing this, one remains assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, basically, mindfulness gets confused if one attends pleasant aspect, which is the feelings that have arose based on the assumed senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through simply attending that pleasure, that's the result of that assumption, you're actually maintaining that assumption through that thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, there is... there is a... you can say the assumption comes first, but not temporally first, but structurally first.
[SPEAKER_01]: The simultaneous presence of the assumption and the feelings that result on account of that assumption, but it's simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like you assume without feeling and then the feeling comes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because it's simultaneous, simply through attending feelings, you're maintaining that which sort of determines those feelings, which is an assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: And at the same time, your mind, eh... well, they're suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of that whole picture, suffering is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that is again the same principle of that simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you can say assumption results in feelings, or assumption results in suffering, or assumption results in craving, or craving results in...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just simultaneously presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just maintaining each other, because you're attending any of it, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the principle gets maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind seems to be confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equals.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, what is...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, assuming the senses means?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, assuming the senses means... means... well, literally, assuming those senses to be yours, or to be for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, assuming senses to be yours, and then assuming that which you gather through those senses to be for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you assume that the sights you see are the sights that your eyes see.
[SPEAKER_01]: The sights are yours, like for you, they're yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're looking at things that are not necessarily yours, the fact that you're looking with your eyes, it's like your sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that sight is for me, any sight of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to start seeing
[SPEAKER_01]: The dead phenomenon of senses, of my senses, it's kind of always a negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't actually see your eye with the same eye, in the same sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can... you end up assuming... well, you end up assuming because the senses are ambiguous.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't really know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a big kind of dark
[SPEAKER_01]: A vague cloud of all senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, all you have is sights, sounds, melted such as for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you just take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you discern long enough, through that repetition, that whatever notion of your senses you might have, that those senses are... Oh, I think my senses are...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you discern that whatever notion you might have,
[SPEAKER_01]: Those senses will never ever be anything more, and certainly will never be anything separable from a fleshy organ of eye, skin, tongue, like literally these organs, random objects in the world, that are put together in the unit of this body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't examine the organs like a doctor would, impersonally, because then it doesn't work, then you don't see that connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see the dependence.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to see your own organs and the only way you can see it is in that external sense of, oh, a lump of flesh, which is my eye, tongue, ears, eardrums.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just organs, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just as you have this bin, broom, stone, tree, eye, liquid, matter,
[SPEAKER_01]: Brain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, four elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, these particular material organs are that because of which there are sights that you can discern in the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not in you, nor is it for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those organs are external, as external as the external objects around you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, you don't see the
[SPEAKER_01]: The connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that connection literally needs to be fabricated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you will never see the connection naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's a secondary... Because natural... natural way is the way of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Natural way is the way that goes with the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to go against the grain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you were to dwell on it long enough, like a fabricating contemplation that your senses
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say my senses, whatever vague thought you might have about it, take it as vague.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to define it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take it as a whole phenomenon, as an entity, that vague thought of my senses, and then see the presence of that as directly determined, inseparable from the fleshy eye, the tongue, the skin, the nose, ears, brain, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: You literally, like, no matter what vague thoughts I might have about my senses, the fact that I can't even think that ambiguously, abstractly, is because this living matter of my body, of this sixth sense base, is present in that material form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when it gets destroyed, I can't think out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how much your mind, your thoughts, your ideal senses might feel different from the material objects, fundamentally, it can never, like, escape it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, destruction of matter will bring an end to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why we're realizing that no matter how much you volitionally, reflexively develop, you know, your thoughts, and your discernments, and your abstractions, and your reflect... whatever, whatever you want,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all there possible, because there is a living sixth sense body present in the world, as a matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that matter gets destroyed, when that material is disintegrated, you can't be conceiving and abstracting in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't know any mental phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter what intentionality you can have with your mind, it's subordinate to the presence of that gratuitous matter that is living.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is your body, which is your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that's taken away, nothing can be left, nothing can remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like contemplating, like drilling, literally drilling that connection, because it's not obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: It seems fabricated, it seems abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is, for Putrajana.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is completely abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the right abstraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the abstraction that, if repeated a sufficient number of times,
[SPEAKER_01]: It will, like, take root, it will correspond to how things actually are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can see how things actually are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is that, yes, your senses cannot even be conceived to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone that which you acquire through your senses to be for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you think now, or if anybody thinks, oh, my, like, my eyes, what is my, my eyes and senses, you immediately assume as inside of you, as internal, as part of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can have just another thought, which is, well, another way of seeing, which is seeing those objects as external, as a thought, because... Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're always going to have a thought, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when I said, ah, that's a thought, that doesn't mean I'm dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just meant that that big is that you think is the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see, no, that's a thought that, obviously, for me, stands for that which I think senses are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you start recognizing that all you're going to have is a phenomenon of thought in regard to your senses, then you realize, well, then, thinking these external organs, it's nothing less real than this thought, because that's also thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the right thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then somebody tells you, somebody else, like the Buddha and the Suttas, tells you that that's the right thought, and if you keep repeating it, it will correspond to how things are, because it's right, and then you can see how things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not without a sufficient amount of repetition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's... that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we spoke about it before.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not... that's why you can't stumble upon āyur-mantra by accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, oh, yeah, I got it, just in a, you know, instantaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was doing this and then this happened.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop it literally through training and drilling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, like in this instance, the Buddha tells you this is the right thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, experience of putusana is top to bottom, is completely wrong, affected by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have a criteria of what is right thought, what it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you have to fit in the Buddha, and the Buddha tells this is the right thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can think that right thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But thinking it once won't make a difference, because you have this whole ocean of ignorance that needs to be drained away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then thinking it twice won't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking it three times won't make a difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you keep thinking it, like, five thousand times, then it will be drained in a way, and eventually, when it's officially drained, you'll recognize, oh, ignorance is drained.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so the point is...
[SPEAKER_01]: That drilling, that doing... that in the beginning, yeah, you have to do it on account of faith, in the sense that, okay, you believe that the Buddha knew what he was talking about, so you have faith, so that's why you're applying that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why you can't do... like, you can sometimes, uh, accidentally, uh, stumble, like, do the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Engage in the right thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't know that that is the right thought, if nobody told you, you will not know that that was the right thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will certainly not repeat it thousand of times without any apparent result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, by chance, you know, you can roll a dice and you can get it once and twice and five times.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't get it hundred.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... just impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable to, like, always get the right result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you know that that is the right result, then you always go for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that utterance of another is one of the, like a, eh... fundamental factors for the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot possibly, as I said, you might have been doing things rightly, attending things rightly, but if nobody externally told you that that is right thing, it's simply inconceivable that you would have stuck to repeating those things rightly
[SPEAKER_01]: Thousands of times for years, because there is no apparent result right away.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like you do it and you immediately see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to keep doing it, and doing it, and doing it, and doing it, and you accept it intellectually as the right thing, like reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: As the Buddha said, oh, the man who wants to be free from suffering goes and, like, frequents the wise men.
[SPEAKER_01]: He listens to what they say.
[SPEAKER_01]: He ponders, makes sense, measures the task, then he does it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you accept it through reasoning, through discernment on that level, but then you keep repeating it, and repeating, and repeating.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because you had faith in what the Buddha said to be right, you stick to it, and you repeat it ten thousands of times, and because it was right, you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you didn't know, if you didn't have faith that it was right, you wouldn't have possibly stuck to it for that long, because there is no... there is no confirmation of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until much, much later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's no confirmation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might have different results.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might have pleasant results, you might have a lessening of suffering or more of an understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: What gives you the motivation to continue?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you haven't had the end... you don't have the end result, but you... it makes sense what the Buddha says, it makes sense, so you follow the teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then... but you're not getting great results or... Well, that's... that's for somebody who has heard the teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that can be an inspiration for them to continue, even without the apparent results.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: But imagine how impossible it is for somebody to continue, who hasn't even heard or accepted, through reasoning and developed faith, that what the Buddha said was right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for them to continue, because there is no... there is absolutely nothing changes through these drillings.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't see nothing, nothing better, no worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just... you won't even notice it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And let alone stick to it and repeat it thousands of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right intention, the avoiding the wrong intention, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Attending to things rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be told.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're told, you can discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you discern it, then you can do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because as you... yeah... as it's... something makes sense to you, so you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, say for example, restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just, you know, keep a strength and aim.
[SPEAKER_00]: He reflects, as he's doing it, he looks and he sees that there is a... the pleasure of being blameless.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's not he's an arahant, he's not a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, ah, that thing is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There are ways of developing wisdom without Buddha's aid, but obviously it will never lead to the
[SPEAKER_01]: The final abandoning of the assumption of self and self-view and arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what I mean, that once you actually heard the Buddha's teaching, and you do follow, you do restrain yourself, but you don't go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know if you understood it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you keep the precepts and you get the joy that comes from that, then you can maybe be a little bit more confident.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're thinking, oh yeah, there might be something more to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: What he says after being restrained and the rest of it might also be true, so I'll continue on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this... on top of that, also, as I said, like, you might be doing things rightly or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because you haven't been told externally, through the suttas and through the Buddha's instruction, what you should be doing,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't really have even the external criteria of what kind of corresponds to what what might be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but then, if you were to develop that criteria, then you can look back at the stuff you used to do, and you can actually, yeah, back then,
[SPEAKER_01]: This such-and-such thing, such-and-such way of attending that I was doing, that was actually right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It corresponds to the dhamma principles, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: It corresponds to how things... Obviously, back then, you didn't know what those principles were, so you couldn't have stuck to it and repeated it long enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't... you can do it by chance once, twice, ten times, but not ten thousands of times by chance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have an anchor to bring you back, which will be the discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you can also look back and see, oh, when I thought I was right in practicing, I was completely wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now you've got the criteria that you can also see things in the past you used to do, your attempts at practice, and so on, and you can see, oh, actually, no, that was not that wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, back then, you didn't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody told you back then, you would have stuck to it, but nobody told you, so it took you longer, or not, it depends.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why it's... it's... it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Alternance of another.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, obviously, means that's why it also needs to have that initial step, first step of faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: That you have faith that this other, the Buddha, the suttas, the arahant, the sotāpanna, might be the Buddha, the sutta, the arahant, the sotāpanna, might know what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, it's not that that faith needs to stay till the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: That faith is the initial push and then, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do it rightly, you'll come to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you won't need faith, or rather, you'll replace the faith with confidence, because now you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: Confirmed confidence in the Buddha, in the Dhamma, in the Saṅgha, replaces that faith in the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to believe in it, because I know it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like... it's this... similar to... something makes sense, you don't know, but it makes the most sense, and then you understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: But always, always in the back of your mind, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a little bit of reserve, because as puthujjana, you don't have a criteria of what really makes... or rather, what makes sense to you as a puthujjana, does not necessarily mean it's the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because often, yeah, it feels right when people are like, oh, I know I'm not a Sotāpanna, but it feels right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, that's a big mistake right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know you don't know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, you're happy to follow what you think you know, while you at the same time say, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're just like undermining yourself within the same sentence.
[SPEAKER_00]: This connection with the Buddha says dhamma is leading onwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, anyone can read that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And is that maybe not it?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, again, you need to discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, I'm sure that people who think dhamma leading, like, upanayaka means leading inwards, or leading onwards, or...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm sure that they're convinced that that is what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to be completely self-transparent and see, okay, so, do I really hold on to this belief just because it's pleasing to me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just because it suits my other beliefs, or is it because it really, really makes sense after, like, deep, profound, repetitive, tedious drilling, investigation and contemplation?
[SPEAKER_01]: When you know that you have not, kind of, just covered it up, like, oh, no, no, no, I believe in this, it's fine, but you really drilled into it and there was nothing left unturned, then, okay, it's least likely to be wrong, because you really drilled through it, through the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the attitude you always have to have.
[SPEAKER_01]: But most often, people just maintain beliefs, because it helps them maintain their previous beliefs, helps them maintain their previous beliefs, and then, so it's just like maintenance of their beliefs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they all do that for one reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pleasing to me, as the sūtra say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's... when it's, eh... what is leading onwards?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, leading onwards, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you were to understand, for example, what dhamma is,
[SPEAKER_01]: That understanding will be taking you further and further and further till the other end.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's leading you onwards through that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not a theory.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not an abstraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not something you can accept or reject.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something whereby, through understanding, you're going further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you realize there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through that understanding, through that criteria, there is more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until, as Arahants or when the Buddha described, says, ah, there is no beyond this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's leading onwards, naturally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... like, if dhamma is presented as an explanation that you can accept or not, take it or leave it, that's not leading onwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's an explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, done, right in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why often the common-player interpretations, they kind of lay it out, and then you just read it and say, OK, so that's how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is no panaika element in that, because, OK, that's how it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha, whenever he would be, like in all of the suttas, and I think I told you that the other day, he never... like, no matter what approach he would take on in expounding dhamma to a person or to a group of people, he would follow that approach through to the final point of arhanty, freedom from suffering, whatever, even if those people don't necessarily achieve it, his instruction would go all the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't stop halfway through his
[SPEAKER_01]: approach that through understanding of nāmarūpa and the all, you can become an arahant and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: He wouldn't stop halfway through and then say, well, as a matter of fact, nāmarūpa also corresponds to the five aggregates, and then start comparing it linearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can... it does correspond.
[SPEAKER_01]: This experience as a whole, whether you take it as five aggregates or nāmarūpa-viññāṇa, viññāṇa-nāmarūpa,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, this and that, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you start comparing it, it ceases to be that open icon, like, leading on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it ceases to be dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because dhamma is dhamma only when it leads you out of suffering, when it leads you towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can be talking the dhamma, like, dhamma terms and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is, it's not leading on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't even, by accident, teach dhamma to somebody else, without you yourself understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that open-eyed element is not... it's something you can't... something you can understand and know, and then convey to another person, in the right term, knowing what, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, knowing what to say for them to understand, not sort of comparing dhamma and comparing the principles and the terminology for the sake, like, for the scholarly sake by itself, in itself, and then present it as a kind of, okay, here's a theory, here's my explanation, and it's like, okay, sure, I accept that, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You leave it at that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a person who understood, like an arahant or the Buddha, would know that, because that's what understanding is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, they wouldn't be teaching as a form of explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're explaining something, ah, okay, it makes sense, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, when you're leading somebody onwards in their understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sure, I could compare, like, if nāmarūpa, viññāṇa, vipassana, if, as a whole, that approach is leading you onwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if we are just doing it for the sake of
[SPEAKER_01]: Debate, like abstract reasoning, or whatever, just theory, or just because it's pleasing to me, that's just pointless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if we actually talk about dhamma all the time, we're not, because there is no leading-on-ones element.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, you can see leading-on-ones, like when I said about the assumption of the senses, I could have said, well, see, that's because you think your senses are yours, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so I should think my senses are not, not mine, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just linear and there is absolutely no...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if I tell you, well, actually, you have to stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see that your senses, the thought of what you think your senses are, is inseparable from that material thought, again, of the fleshy eye and all of the other sense bases.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to keep drilling that connection on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just once, okay, that this is not mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to discern it and see dependent upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you will have, like, if you abandon your senses, means then the feelings won't be generated, which means then the mindfulness will not be clouded, which means the suffering won't arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will feel that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will feel the absence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, I could say to myself, senses are not mine, but it doesn't make sense, makes any no difference to the suffering that you experience or that you might experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Suffering that you might be liable to, makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it makes no difference, means it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're actually reading the suttas, but it's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you attend to things rightly, and you undo the assumption of your senses, so, through that undoing, you are actually, like, not liable to that suffering anymore, and you can know that, you know, this is dhamma, because it's directly freeing you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in order to be able to see that, to discern that, you need to be completely self-transparent, and not act out of this view is simply pleasing to me, that's why I'm holding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to be ready to have some very displeasing views,
[SPEAKER_01]: Some views that will fill you with anxiety, and everything else that follows, because you're undoing, like, your own assumption of your own very existence, of your own sense of self, of your own confidence as a person, or as a whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're undoing all of that, and using only criteria of absence of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see, like, oh, well, this, actually, I'm not just acting because it's pleasing, this is really the real thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, look at that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to find out the next moment that that is not a real thing, would you be filled with terror and anxiety?
[SPEAKER_01]: You would.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it's not a real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a real thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as I said, the approach that you took, like, like, oh, I'm gonna hold this view because it's pleasing to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like, okay, that's not good, that's not wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'm gonna hold this view, but I'm not doing it because it's pleasing to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fine?
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be true, but then look at that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look whereby, if that view is taken away from you, or if you find out that it's wrong, would you be affected personally?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, thoroughly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, yes, I would.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that view might not be wrong, but I'm certainly holding on to it, because if that view is gone, I'll experience this anxiety and terror, which means I need to take it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a way, you are still holding, because it's pleasing to you, even if it's the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're holding a view regardless of it giving you pleasure or giving you pain,
[SPEAKER_00]: But yet, it just... you can't see it any other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... you know, it's... Well, first of all, you can, but not hold any views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not... it's not... you can only go beyond them as an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But before that, you can only hold the right views on account of wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you can hold the wrong views and not have any right views.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, the whole notion of, oh, I don't hold to any views, that's a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, there was that sutta that I'm actually referring to.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he said, oh, he said, Buddha asked him, so what, what views do you have?
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, ah, Master Gautama, I have, uh, what did he say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, I have no, I have no...
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, he asked him, what views are pleasing to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: He's like, no, Master Gautama, I don't accept any views.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have no views.
[SPEAKER_01]: No views are pleasing to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, well, surely that view is pleasing to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not holding to any views, it's also a view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to discern that.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, oh, just stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just contradicting yourself right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same sense, if you believe you're not holding to any views, you're kind of in limbo, hovering over, that's a view that you are clearly not aware of.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you don't become aware of it, you can't abandon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to recognize you have no choice but to hold the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you can choose is develop the right views,
[SPEAKER_01]: At the expense of wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, hold the right views, then, because they're right, they will take you eventually beyond the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even then, I'm not holding any views.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: I went beyond the views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, holding or not holding, or both holding, and neither holding or not holding, simply doesn't apply anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You dropped it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, isn't that, eh, another sutta, thirty-eight?
[SPEAKER_00]: Manjhima Nukkāna, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh, this, this right view,
[SPEAKER_00]: As pleasing as it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: As pure, as bright.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to hold on to this view, you would not be...
[SPEAKER_00]: Practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Practicing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would not understand the dhamma to be a raft.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, that's like, that's what, that's what would happen to, to ārya-sāvakas who were not, who didn't reach ārahantship.
[SPEAKER_01]: who kind of got complacent, like sotāpanna, sākāni, nidāsutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, basically, they got, you know, and yeah, the great mass of suffering has been destroyed and so on, and they're pleased with that, which means they won't be pushing their view further, they'll just hold on to it, because they're satisfied with what they got, basically, they got complacent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what will happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, even the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, oh, so that... no, that's not a bad thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's a bad thing from... or rather, it's not a fully adequate thing from the point of view of an arahant, but from pratyūjana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, please, by all means, everybody should try and get the right view and hold on to it daily, rather than the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, actually, holding on to the right view
[SPEAKER_01]: It's... well, you can... because it's a right view, because you have the right view, you have the right criteria, you can see that you're holding on to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can, like, not exert yourself in practice further, but you'll know.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's particularly the danger is you don't know that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't know that you are holding on to those views.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you don't know, there's absolutely no way you can abandon them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's much more dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Going back to something making sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, you have faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: OK, that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's always your own effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to... there's always this... your own effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even though it makes sense, you're also going to be authentic enough to see that there is no... even though this is pleasant, this idea, this view that this monk says, and I really believe what he says,
[SPEAKER_00]: But I don't really experience what he says, because I haven't made that effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: I haven't made that effort, so how can I really know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Making that effort is when I say, ah, you need to do the drilling, on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Drilling of the right contemplation, right attending, drilling of not tolerating unwholesome states, not tolerating sensual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are drilling, all this hard work, internal work.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, that's basically 99%.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the same sense, well, what this such-and-such monk said, it makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start applying it, and then you actually know it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you will know why it's wrong, and where it's wrong, and how it's wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's also this kind of... you can actually see what to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that not only makes sense,
[SPEAKER_00]: But you you're able to see what you have to do with the bud.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you're leaning onwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the other bit in the sutra.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says he measures the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know exactly
[SPEAKER_01]: How much?
[SPEAKER_01]: What needs to be done?
[SPEAKER_01]: What needs?
[SPEAKER_01]: The task that is measured.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, he listens.
[SPEAKER_01]: He hears this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: This sounds promising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he ponders on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gets some understanding through reasoning and acceptance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by having an understanding, that's already like almost like a beginning of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: By having that discernment, then he can...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so this is what needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most of the people today, like monks or lay people, when it comes to practice, it's just this vast, ambiguous blur of everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: What needs to be done?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just, you know, be here, now, yesterday, tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as if you have a choice, but to be here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where else can you be?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just this ambiguous, weird, mystical... Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they haven't measured the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you didn't assume this, and the Buddha would clearly say, and people understood, would clearly say, this needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... and...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, knowing what needs to be done, even it's patujana, requires some development of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, measuring the task is actually quite a significant stage, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Know, okay, if I do this,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I could expect that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, if I were to apply myself in such a manner, for a certain period of time, I don't know exactly for how long, but if I keep applying myself in this manner, to that extent, I might be on the way to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And having it like that, measure the task, you won't need any external inspiration.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't need
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you measure the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the end goal, you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you can't blame it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't actually... you're beyond blaming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your circumstances...
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes, like the Sutta said, to be known in the personal, individually, by the wise, by those who develop wisdom, to measure the task, to apply themself, and then to reach the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like saying, uh, you see what's... Ah, there is nothing to be attained, there is nothing to be done, there is nothing... Find me the Sutta that says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't, because I read them all.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you'll find it in other schools of Buddhism and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they themselves haven't measured the task, haven't developed discernment to be able to have the tools to measure the task.
[SPEAKER_01]: And all that's because they haven't been transparent from the beginning, self-transparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were, if you were transparent, you would always be coming from the place of, I want to be free from suffering, which means you'll never cover it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how pleasing the view is, how pleasing the teacher is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this freeing me from suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll give it a bit more.
[SPEAKER_01]: More time, more time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're applying yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if it's still not making a difference to your suffering, you will drop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will move on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that criteria is the fundament.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the criteria that, yes, that Patujana can trust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, full transparent freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, okay, this might be freeing me from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you stop and think.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody is to take away
[SPEAKER_01]: This particular practice that I started engaging in, that I think is freeing me from suffering, would I suffer on account of that?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I would.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you practice on that level even further, and then you'll see whether what you were doing was actually freeing you from suffering, or you were just holding on to it because it was pleasing to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what if you, what if you, you... Do you want to check on them?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or if you have a view that... a view that no one can take away, that's... that's the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That no matter what way you think of it, well, you can't actually reverse it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't see things in a different way.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you... you... you could try... you would have to focus on... Not the exit, but doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the facet of doubt disappears.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can reach the right view by fully, transparently doubting any views that you hold.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, don't hold back, don't leave anything unturned.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that which is left cannot be accessed by that full-on cultivated doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see, like, you know, you can doubt this, you can doubt that, but you can't doubt
[SPEAKER_01]: The presence of doubt, which means there is a there is a thing present, which means there is a nature of that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And be it doubt or something else, you can't doubt the presence of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what dhamma pertains to.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take that course and then you'll be just kind of going further and further away from any doubt, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's happiness present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's restlessness present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's sensuality present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, there's doubt present.
[SPEAKER_01]: What all those things have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: A thing is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's no doubt about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no doubt that can even access that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can doubt particular aspects of an arising thing, but you can't doubt the arising of the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why the insight of sotāpanna comes from that very popular... Whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever has the nature of arising, has the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't say this, which has the... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever, be it doubt, be it sensuality, be it happiness, be it sadness... Whatever has the nature of arising, for that reason,
[SPEAKER_01]: As the nature of ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, for that reason, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's another topic.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might have spoken about it in different talks as well, but things are not impermanent because you watch their destruction, watch their disappearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're impermanent because they arose.
[SPEAKER_01]: They came to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why they're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: One could have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what else to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: One could have that view, or not doubt that, that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: One could see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, eh, do you think it's possible to not have, eh... you're not necessarily released from dukkha?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You won't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes, it takes now repetition of that, that right view
[SPEAKER_01]: On and on and on, until it kind of saturates your experience as a whole, and flushes out all the ignorance and avidya.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still have no doubt, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think that, like, no, you can have... Well, you can have no doubt, but whether... but, like, that's just the first step.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you have to keep applying that view, which is inaccessible to doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're not applying it, you're just holding that view, and you're not
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like doing anything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go to the great view of... that's beyond the doubt.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not necessarily sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's not necessarily... and that's why you have even those like dhamma-nusāri and sadhana-nusāri, those kind of putujanas, they were attained to the path, but they were not sotāpannas yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this sot... is this sot... dhamma-nusāri and sadhana-nusāri, whether they came through faith or they came through the dhamma investigation and reasoning.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will arrive at the path eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you can get the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, as I said, it's a gradual drilling, repetition, that it's sort of, like, bit by bit by bit by bit undoing your ignorance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as the Buddha said, you can't say, oh, today my ignorance has been undone this much, yesterday that much, tomorrow it will be this much.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's like, like the carpenter using the axe every day for years,
[SPEAKER_01]: Every day he grabs that axe.
[SPEAKER_01]: The handle is wearing thin.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he can't say, yesterday from today, oh, this is how much it wore off.
[SPEAKER_01]: But after a year of using it, he can come and one day he can go, oh, my goodness, my axe handle is very thin.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look, completely worn out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here is a person who is gone beyond doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that person would see, then, that it's... he can't doubt his view, but he's not getting any further on account of his own effort that he's making or not making, the amount of strength that he's putting into the practice or furthering their view or developing their view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, so, not only is you beyond doubt, but you're also beyond doubt that any further development is due to my own effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, whatever was to be obtained by the manly eye for man is straight eye, I've obtained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it's completely on you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just others, or, like, people, and even other circumstances, it's irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as you have the living functioning mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: As you say, once you get the right view, there is nothing standing in between you and Arahantship, except your lack of effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing else that can come in the way, which is why it can't be taken away, because it wasn't given to you externally either.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's something you developed fully, and it's like a one-way, one-way development.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But nothing except yourself stands in the way, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't remember this quote.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a Stoic thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says that a God is made free from all troubles on account of nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the sage is free from all trouble.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of his own effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of his own effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he's better.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's even stronger than the God.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he's not... Well, exactly, he's stronger than the God, because God was not strong, because they were given.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because they were just given to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were given.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you took it for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't have to develop anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're seeing the senses again, as external, external things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I think about my eye, I see that as an external thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: But my eye says she...
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem there is that in regard to that thought, you're having like a tacit, implicit assumption that the eye is something more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can think your thoughts, I think, while you at the same time assume to find your eye in the direction of internal, inside of you, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at yourself in the mirror, that eye that you see in the mirror, that is that eye because of which you're able to look at that eye in the mirror in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: That very reflection there, of that fleshy organ, is that object
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're saying it doesn't go further than what...
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no further than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It closes upon itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The assumption takes you further into infinity, whereby you would see the reflection of yourself, seeing the reflection of yourself, seeing the reflection, and think, wow!
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, all the whole thing would be swept in a second, if you remove the flesh you are, if you destroy it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole infinity of your perception, whatever else, it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It might be infinite, but it doesn't last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you flash your eyes, gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Accident, death, sickness, aging, whatever, gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole infinity is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your sight is gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that flashed your eye was that because of which the whole domain of sight was present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why that's... and you'll never see like a one, two, three, four, five, a linear connection.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you have to contemplate, you have to fabricate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning, it's abstract, but that's only because it doesn't apply to your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to make it apply to your experience, whereby you have to drill in, on and on and on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Drill in a thought, literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Estab... like... define it, think it, and then establish it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thought that those fleshy organs are that because of which I am alive here, thinking, intending, looking, smelling, touching.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those fleshy organs disappear.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of this cannot remain standing even for a split second longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the beginning, it's an abstract thought, but you keep drilling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it will stay longer and longer and longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, when it stays long enough, you start seeing things through that thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start seeing things through the right view, when it takes root.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you say those senses, those senses are
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing more than what I experienced now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is, that is the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What I say, the flesh organ, that, what I think, that is it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's something you also see through your senses, but that you can know that is that, because of which your senses are there in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of turning... Well, it's, yeah, yeah, it's like a, like, kind of closes upon itself, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't go... it's not anywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Other than...
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, look yourself in the mirror, look at your eyes in the mirror, and you'll see how you assume, like, as if you were behind them, inside, somewhere, left or right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you then don't let your thought, or rather if you anchor your thought in that reflection of that fleshy organ,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you look yourself in the mirror, and you'll see your eyes, and then you can, okay, this whole, like, the face, and the flesh, and the nose, and stuff, you can kind of see that, okay, that's just organs.
[SPEAKER_01]: But pin it down to the iris in your eyes, and you kind of think the life is behind that, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you look at it, what you see, you see a black circle, a black dot, in the center of that flesh you're holding.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It stops there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It starts there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't go beyond that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that flesh that I'm looking at.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that because of which I'm able to look?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there are like two dimensions simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: One is this material dimension of a fleshy eye, and the one is like simultaneously present dimension of awareness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is not like a linear that behind the eyes, it goes and you look, you know, eyes are like the window into the soul.
[SPEAKER_01]: They aren't.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just a flat wall.
[SPEAKER_01]: The soul is in front of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thoughts are in front of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't access that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can't enter it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They separate the plane.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's that assumption of that quick eye movement that makes you, well, makes you maintain that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, it's not the assumption of quick eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eyes move fast.
[SPEAKER_01]: It makes you, like, helps you maintain that assumption easily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, the
[SPEAKER_01]: Your intentionality is measured by the movement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things you do, things you intend with your body, with your speech, with your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say your whole body is paralyzed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can always, like, move the eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically when the eyes are motionless, well, it's dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, eyes are dead.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even those eyes, the quickest moving, it's still just flesh yoga.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, your hand is, your nails are, and your hair is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your spectacles are, your robes are flesh, material, matter, rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this matter is there because of which there is that awareness in regard to it anyway, in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's just like two completely separate
[SPEAKER_01]: Domains of matter and that awareness in regard to the matter inseparable from each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't have one without the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just think matter, because, as I said, you're thinking matter, which means there's awareness in regard to matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nor can you just have pure awareness, which is ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you have pure awareness if your method is destroyed?
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can assume that there is a pure awareness, the divine, whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you see the truth about your body, yourself, too.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or certainly, you... it will always remain an assumption, because you can never find out that there is a... that there is an assumption... oh, sorry, an awareness free from your... free from the material aspect of life of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in good faith, that is, because you can't, if you look at it, if you look at your experience as a whole, and even if you conceive it, no matter how pleasing that conception is, that your awareness can be separate, the very reality of your practice, of the present moment, shows you that, well, I'm thinking that my awareness is separate, while I'm all determined by this matter, thus I'm not separate.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can only assume it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, you can only assume the matter as independent of you, because that's the thought, which is you, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why matter finds footing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It finds footing, basically, in your experience, because you provided, you assumed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you see the flesh here, I... You're saying pure matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the four great elements find footing in how you conceive the existence of matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you assume the eyes are yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means those eyes have found a footing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those fleshy lumps organs have found a footing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They exist for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, all you're going to see are fleshy eyes moving left and right, whatever, with a black iris in the center.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all of that is out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you go through that black iris, you just find, you know, blood and liquid and whatever else eyes have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is no... there is that direction of matter and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You drill further, you'll find matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: More matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the same matter, depending how generally you look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what you have to do is stop assuming that you are behind that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can stop assuming that you're behind that matter if you drill long enough, thought, that you are not behind that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to keep drilling and drilling it and drilling it until it takes root.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when it does, then seeing your own eyes, your own movement, your own senses, will not induce that assumption of self behind those senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: We spoke about, I don't know, non-descending into the mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's, you know, that's a whole... Not descending into your eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not descending into your eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not descending into matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not taking up matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not assuming it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in more practical terms, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Being mindful of your body as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: means your mind won't descend into it, so to speak, whereby you'll end up acting, performing bodily acts carelessly, not descending into your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, your mind not descending into your mouth will make you aware of what you're saying and what is coming out of your mouth.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it won't make you act carelessly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, not having your citta descend, like, in your own mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't get complacent there, which means that even your thoughts you'll be aware of and you won't be thinking carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't descend or mindful in a proper way of your mind, as an external, seeing it externally, in a proper way,
[SPEAKER_00]: Just holding that where you're seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then we can start talking about jhānas.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, that's... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you make a practice out of it, out of establishing your mind, well, upon the certain things, like thinking and pondering, overcoming the speech determination and so on, then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there are many different ways of establishing your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhānas are just one of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, establish your mind upon the perception of forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you go into town, none of the perceptions that come from the town can access you, or bother you, or cause you harm, because your mind is established upon the great perception of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you recognize, okay, so I'm free from the disturbances that come based on the perceptions that... from the town, but if there are perceptions that... if there are disturbances coming on account of perceptions in the forest, I will be disturbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why don't I develop my mind, or rather establish my mind upon something even greater, so that then even the forest cannot disturb me?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then you can establish your mind upon the perception of earth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But establishing your mind on the perception of earth doesn't mean actually holding the perception of earth in front of you?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically finding it, like discerning it in things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you don't need to hold it, because it's already implied in those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not fabricating anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not creating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The most obvious, maybe a bit crude example, would be, well, what does town, and forest, and the mountains, and the oceans, for that matter, have in common?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's an arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that arisen thing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Those arisen things, what do they have in common?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they do have in common the fact that they're on Earth, that they're Earth, they're part of Earth, that they have the solid aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: That phenomenon of solidity, or immovability, or Earth, you want to call it, you establish your mind upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an abstraction now, because your mind is not established.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you have it at the background of your mind,
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, anchored in the notion of solid in everything, even the running water, your mind will get established.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how the casinos work, in the same sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what casinos are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you would establish your mind in...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing that comes on a particular level can disturb you, because your mind has been established to that much greater element of solidity in everything particular that you experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you literally surpass
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole domain of particular things, which is everything, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you... if you... about the thought, like you have a... once you establish your mind on thought, general thought, so any thought that you have, or you establish your mind on mind... Well, that would be the casino of consciousness, which is the most refined of all of them, and it would come kind of last.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, you can just establish your mind upon the general experience as a whole, right here, right now, but make sure that it's not divorced from that material aspect, the material end of it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, if you come from the material end of it, you make sure you don't overlook that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you are here now,
[SPEAKER_01]: If there is any disturbance to arise, it will be on account of your presence here, on the hill, in the central Sri Lanka, in this area, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, now you have, like, you know, phones, emails, stuff like that, so disturbance cannot...
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, even that would arise through your current situation here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, on account of your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why there are many different ways of establishing your mind, but it's the same principle of establishing your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the Buddha, when he spoke about the casinos,
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of that, he abandons everything inferior to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is inferior to the phenomenon of earth?
[SPEAKER_01]: That thought of earth, general earth?
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, anything more particular than that is inferior to that phenomenon of earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he said, but obviously, being
[SPEAKER_01]: He's still liable to disturbance on account of the general phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, it's much less disturbance than the particular disturbances that can arise if you're not established upon the element of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, Tathāgata has seen the gratification, the danger in this case, in regard to the casino of Earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing that, he knew it, and he went beyond through that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not bothered by it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, there is establishing mind upon a casino, or whatever, and then there is knowing that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stay in terms of this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, it's not descending into the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not, yeah, not lapsing mindfulness, or, like, and lapsing mindfulness doesn't mean, like, you know, you need to constantly keep your mind in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it means you need to anchor your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can, whether you're talking now, sit
[SPEAKER_01]: Standing, walking, any body posture, means the body's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, the earth element is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, the water element is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, the fire element is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means, the air element is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can take any of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're kind of slightly more refined, but you can just take your thought element, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even take the elements, just take the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't even have to take the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just take... this current posture is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that posture changes, take that posture is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever disturbances can enter you right now, it would be while you're sitting.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be while your body is seated, the senses are liable to such and such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you anchor your mind
[SPEAKER_01]: in the seated position of your body.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you get up, you anchor your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you anchor your mind in the notion of the body is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And obviously, if you're thinking it in front of you, you're not anchored.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're anchored when you stop thinking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're just discerning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're just seeing it in the background of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That... that's what means being anchored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, you throw an anchor and then you forget about it, because you're anchored.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know that it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to keep pulling it out and throwing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to keep holding on to it, because it's anchored.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, leave.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let the boat float, left and right, wherever it wants to go.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it goes too far and starts dragging the anchor, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: if it ceases to be anchored, then restart it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Re-establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm not talking about for, like, sitting, you know, cross-legged and...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking about, like, daily life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anchor your mind in your date.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how... that's what establishing your mind is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he enters and abides the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: He enters and abides this.
[SPEAKER_01]: He establishes his mind and, like, enters and abides the perceptions of forest, and then he goes to the town for pitta pāda or whatever else, and he's not bothered by anything in that town, because his mind is still fully anchored in the perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's no question of acting and doing stuff while you're established, because that's how it works.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what establishment means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, oh, I can establish my mind only when I don't do anything, lock the door and just sit and stare at a wall.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's discerning, the more general.
[SPEAKER_01]: So whether you're here or there or here and there, that means your body has to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a notion of your body
[SPEAKER_01]: Let it be as remote as it wants to be, but have it present in the back of your mind while you're doing other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the important bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: While.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's how we can discern this principle of simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, I'll stop this because I'm doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop only on wholesome stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that obviously undermines the whole picture.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, while you're anchored,
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even if you don't do anything, that's a form of doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am refraining from activity which is my current activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while my mind is active, established in the presence of the body there, I'm refraining from any particular activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as you're mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that correct sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not mindful like in a, you know, like modern psychology sense or whatever, new age sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, just be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindfulness needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: The principle of anchoring needs to be... that's satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that, you need the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while you're sitting here, thinking, trying to formulate the next question, or the same, or the clarification, you can still have a vague, distant, ambiguous notion of your body present at the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's practice of anchoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't require the direct effort, because if it's a direct effort, it means it's not anchoring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you start with a direct effort, only to leave it kind of seep in the background, without losing sight of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And eventually, it becomes effortless, because you can't lose the sight of it, because the particular instances of this body are maintained in the nature of bodies there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's right there in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyhow, the earth element is right there for as long as you're alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to keep thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to let it go in the background and then discern it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you discern it there, then, well, that kind of becomes a foreground almost.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind is established.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the boundary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneous presence.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the boundary of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the body and everything else that's happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but what do you mean by boundary?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that's the extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, whatever else is happening, whatever else happened, whatever might happen, it will happen for as long as... or on account of the presence of the body right here, right there, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you don't... so then you don't... Then you don't chase after it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to, oh, well, how did this happen in the past?
[SPEAKER_01]: How did all of this happen?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you know, for as long as... That's where, on the other hand, we kind of completely remove the ignorance whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, any disturbances that are left are on account of this, like, living body right here, until that body breaks apart, and then even that won't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that disturbance for him is just a disturbance of, you know, pain, enduring, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not disturbance in terms of causing him suffering and dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's beyond that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a nuisance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any nuisance that was left, it's on account of this body for as long as it's functioning.
[SPEAKER_01]: When that breaks apart, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There won't be another body taken up.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing is, eh... things like, eh... if one does the practice correctly, well, there's no assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no assuming, eh... the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're practicing in a way, you're not so... mindful, it's not becoming confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could experience nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sotāpanna experienced nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he's not established.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's not established, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, like, kutujanas can experience nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because they're kutujanas, they won't be a nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in terms of the experience, it is that which Nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārāja Mahārā
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he goes to the point where he says, he thinks, I am... this is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm entering nibbāna with nibbāna's mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, although that is actually a nibbāna, what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: He is not established on it, nor discerning, nor having it developed, because he's still thinking, I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nibbāna is just basically experience without greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagine if you establish yourself in that 24-7, until it takes its roots, and then it just goes off on its own, and you can drop the whole thing, and there is absolutely no cracks in the wall anymore, that nothing can enter you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just done.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sometimes
[SPEAKER_01]: All the Buddha would give would be the general instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, abstain from anything unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cultivate wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thank you, Lord.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm going to retreat now for three months and practice this profound teaching you just gave me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they come out and they're Arahants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, fundamentally, it is just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have to stick to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stick to it to the point of complete self-transparency, no maintaining of beliefs and views,
[SPEAKER_01]: on account of being pleasing to you, not maintaining, on account of protection of anxiety, because you're afraid, not account of maintaining it, sorry, not maintaining it, on account of, well, sensuality, fear, anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just you have to really, like, open up internally for it, and stick to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it will undo things, and then you will see it undoing, and then you'll know that it's working.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, understanding what nibbāna is, like, not just, oh, this... but knowing rightly what nibbāna is, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: not appropriating it, as bhutujjana, means becoming sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, establishing yourself in that nibbāna, eventually, means becoming an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, guarding the senses and restraining will prevent the proliferation of that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, just restraint for somebody who doesn't know what else to look for, it won't amount to much more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, guarding is innocent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Guarding should prevent the kind of habits that you know are wrong and based upon the wrong assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Preventing them from spreading and being establishing and just harassing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, obviously, when you're not leaking left and right, then you'll address what's there contained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, that's why it's strained.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīla has to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I read the translation, undying, ah, undying, like there's things on a wave, you're not pushed around anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see the extent of things, and there's no more jumping over, seeming more than there is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's proliferation, thrown left and right, up and down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fueled by desire and craving and confusion and doubt and all the other factors.